INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to today's lecture
about the last part
of road, which aims to mitigate
observed and unobserved
confounding in
observational data.
You already know that
road 1 addresses observed
confounding via
prognostic matching
and unobserved confounding
when the treatment
effect is known a priori.
Road 2 emulates a target RCT,
randomized clinical trial,
when we have a suitable
trial to mirror.
Now, today, we're going to look
at road 3, which is designed
for the hardest setting.
We have observational data.
Both observed and unobserved
confounding are present.
And there is no reference
trial or prior knowledge
about the treatment
effect to anchor us.
Our goal is to recover
credible treatment effects
and enable precision medicine
under exactly those conditions.
Now, let me start with
a motivating example
from GIST, which stands for
gastrointestinal intestinal
stromal tumor and is a type of
cancer in the digestive tract.
In GIST, adjuvant
imatinib is widely used.
And randomized
clinical trial evidence
indicates it's highly
effective, with a hazard
ratio of approximately
0.46, well below 1.
As a reminder, a hazard ratio
compares the instantaneous risk
of the event between groups.
A value below 1 indicates a
benefit for the treated group.
So a hazard ratio of 0.46
means the imatinib group
has about a 54% lower hazard
of the event than observation
over the study period.
In other words, we
know from trials
that imatinib
substantially reduces risk.
After using the raw
observational data,
we can train an
optimal policy tree,
and we observe that,
for the most patients,
the tree actually prescribes
observation instead of imatinib.
This doesn't match our
clinical intuition.
So why is there
this mismatch when
we train the OPT, the
optimal policy tree?
The reason lies
in the difference
between randomized clinical
trials and observational data.
In randomized clinical
trials, people
are assigned to treatment
groups completely randomly.
These randomization
guarantees that the treated
and the untreated cohorts are
similar to each other in terms
of their characteristics,
and there
is no factor that led to the
prescription of the treatment
to half of them.
Observational data,
on the other hand,
don't have this
randomization feature.
The assignment of patients
to treatment groups
is driven by their
information, which means
that they carry confounding.
There are two main
types of confounding--
observed, which can be
explained by patient differences
in observed features,
like their age,
their size of a tumor they might
have, their sex, et cetera.
There are many
approaches in literature
that aim to mitigate
observed confounding,
like covariate adjustment,
propensity matching, propensity
weighting, and others.
The second type of
confounding is unobserved
and is due to drivers of
prognosis and treatment choice
that we don't know about, like,
for example, mutations that
can affect patient
outcomes, but they might not
be known during the
treatment assignment.
Existing methods in
literature generally
operate under the assumption
that unobserved confounding
does not exist.
So they usually try to validate
this assumption in their data
and then ignore it
in their analysis.
That is the central
point road 3 addresses.
Can we de-bias
observational cohorts
sufficiently to get rid of
both types of confounding?
In the previous lectures, as
we briefly mentioned earlier,
you explored road 1 and road 2.
As a quick recap,
road 1 addresses
observed confounding by matching
on prognosis and normalized
features and, when an
external effect size is known,
can adjust for residual
unobserved confounding via row
weighting.
However, it does not
generalize to cohorts
where the treatment
effect is unknown.
Road 2, on the other hand,
builds on road 1's toolkit
to emulate a specific trial.
It works well when
a suitable target
RCT, randomized
clinical trial, exists.
But it does not apply when
no trial anchor is available.
This leaves us with
the key question--
how do we estimate
treatment effects
and then perform precision
medicine with observational data
without a trial anchor when
both observed and unobserved
confounding are present?