INSTRUCTOR: In this final
part of the lecture,
our goal is to identify patients
who benefit from treatment,
but now using interpretable
AI applied directly
to randomized trial data.
This might seem to
contradict the implications
of row two, where we emphasized
the power and flexibility
of using real-world data.
So why return to RCTs now?
Because we need to directly
compare our method,
optimal policy trees, to
the current gold standard
for subgroup discovery in RCTs.
The one variable at a
time subgroup analysis.
This is the
conventional approach
where researchers stratify
the RCT population
by individual variables, like
tumor size, age, or biomarker
status, and test whether
the treatment effect differs
across strata.
But as we will see next, this
approach has major limitations.
And that's where the power of
interpretable AI really shines.
Let's pause here to contrast the
two approaches, optimal policy
trees versus conventional
subgroup analysis.
A few words on the
conventional approach.
These analyses stratify patients
based on one variable at a time,
say, tumor location,
histologic subtype, or age.
Then they compare treatment
effects within those strata.
For example, older
versus younger patients.
But here is the issue.
Patients don't differ
based on one factor only.
They differ across many.
In addition, when you
test multiple variables
independently, you run
into the classic problem
of multiple hypothesis
testing, which
inflates the risk of
spurious positive findings.
In contrast,
optimal policy trees
do something very different.
They begin by predicting
each patient's outcome
under both treatment scenarios.
For example,
recurrence-free survival
with and without radiotherapy.
These predictions are based
on all available covariates
in a counterfactual
model, not just one.
Then, these predictions are
used to train a decision
tree that groups patients based
on similar treatment benefit,
or lack thereof.
What is powerful here is that
OPTs can identify combinations
of clinical features that
drive benefit, rather than just
flagging a single variable.
To compare the performance of
conventional subgroup analysis
and optimal policy
trees, let me walk you
through a clinical example.
We're looking at retroperitoneal
sarcoma, RPS, a rare cancer
that accounts for about 15%
of all soft tissue sarcomas.
The primary
treatment is surgery,
but there is
ongoing debate about
whether preoperative radiation
therapy, or RT, should be added.
Because RPS is so rare, no RCT
had been conducted for decades.
So for years, investigators
relied on real-world data.
One highly cited RWD study,
published in The Lancet
Oncology, used
propensity score matching
and other rigorous methods.
They found a strong
association between RT
and improved recurrence-free
and overall survival.
But in 2020, the STRASS
trial, the first and only RCT
in this setting, was published.
It found no benefit
from adding radiation.
The discrepancy between the
RWD and the RCT findings
raised a fundamental issue
we have mentioned before.
Even with the best methods,
observational studies cannot
fully address
unobserved confounding.
That, along with
possible differences
in inclusion criteria, likely
explains the conflicting
results.
Back to STRASS.
In an attempt to find
treatment-responsive subgroups
in this overall negative
trial, the investigators
performed conventional
one variable
at a time subgroup analysis.
They reported benefit in
certain histologic subtypes,
but these results were
immediately challenged.
Letters to the editor pointed
out the risk of false positives
due to multiple testing.
Others cited these subgroup
results as a justification
to use RT in clinical practice.
The debate turned chaotic.
We applied optimal
policy trees directly
within the STRASS RCT data set.
So unlike in previous
parts of this lecture,
nothing confounding was needed.
This was randomized data.
But here is what is interesting.
Our findings did not
align with the results
of the conventional
subgroup analysis.
The conventional analysis, shown
on the left side of the slide,
claimed that all
well-differentiated and all
the differentiated patients
benefited from radiation.
However, even in
their own forest plot,
these findings were not
statistically significant.
The confidence intervals
for the hazard ratios
extended beyond one.
In contrast, the
OPT approach, shown
on the right side of
the slide, revealed
a much more nuanced and
biologically plausible story.
Among the differentiated
liposarcoma patients, only those
without R2 rejections, meaning
complete or near-complete tumor
removal, actually
benefited from radiation.
Among well-differentiated
liposarcoma patients,
benefit was seen only
in those under 60 years
old, which is a well-known
subset with worse baseline
prognosis.
Let's now look at the validation
of the conventional analysis
on the left side of the slide
and compare the findings
on the right side of
the slide internally
using Kaplan-Meier plots.
The conventional analysis
on the upper left
examined all well-differentiated
patients as a whole.
But as shown in the
Kaplan-Meier plots,
there was no statistically
significant benefit.
In contrast, the OPT
analysis on the upper right
identified a more
refined subgroup,
well-differentiated
patients under age 60.
And within this
group, we observed
a statistically significant
benefit from radiation.
This is important, not
only because it validates
successfully the OPT method,
but it's also interesting
because of how the
OPTs identify benefit.
In this case, benefit
is driven not only
by better response to treatment,
but by higher baseline risk.
Specifically, these
younger patients
had higher baseline
recurrence risk.
So even if the relative
treatment effect
was relatively similar, they
gained more in absolute terms.
That's absolute risk
reduction in action.
In other cases, the
benefit, or lack of it,
has nothing to do
with baseline risk.
It's about whether the patient
is able to respond to treatment.
For example, as shown in the
lower left side of the figure,
the differentiated RPS
patients with R2 rejections
derived no benefit
from radiation.
Why?
Because the tumor was
not completely removed,
so radiation
couldn't do its job.
This is a classic case
of a treatment effect
modifier, a factor that changes
the relative benefit of therapy.
Look now and compare the
Kaplan-Meier plots on the lower
left and right side.
Baseline prognosis is
similar, but the vertical gap
between curves differs
because the relative risk
reduction is greater
when we exclude patients
with R2 resection.
So why do optimal policy trees
outperform conventional subgroup
analysis?
I believe the
reason is intuitive.
Conventional subgroup analysis
looks at one factor at a time,
like histologic subtype or age.
But in reality, patients
differ across a constellation
of clinical features,
not just one.
And that's where OPTs.
excel.
They integrate multiple
variables simultaneously,
allowing the algorithm to
triangulate more precisely
which combinations of features
define subgroups with varying
treatment response or benefit.
This multidimensional approach
reflects the complexity
of real patients and leads
to more accurate, clinically
meaningful subgroup
identification.
And perhaps just as important,
the method is objective.
OPTs do not rely on
manually selecting
variable combinations or
arbitrary cutoff points.
They let the data drive
the structure, guided
by interpretable
rule-based learning.