INSTRUCTOR: The key idea
in ROAD3 is twofold.
First, we perform prognostic
matching exactly as in ROAD1
to mitigate observed
confounding by aligning patients
on baseline prognosis and
normalized covariates.
Second, we estimate and
balance a latent unobserved
prognostic factor at
the patient level.
Intuitively, this factor--
and I'll call it U tilde--
captures the portion
of a patient's risk
for a bad outcome that remains
unexplained after accounting
for observed covariates
and our prognostic model.
If we balance this latent
signal across treatment arms
in addition to ROAD1's
balancing of observed features
and prognosis, the
cohort should behave
as if randomized with respect
to both observed influences
and the aggregate
unobserved ones.
After these two steps, we fit a
standard multi-variable survival
model on the transformed cohort
to obtain the final hazard ratio
and estimate the final
treatment effect.
That's the ROAD3
pipeline in a nutshell.
Next, we'll unpack
how we estimate
and how we balance these
unobserved latent factor
of step two in practice.
Now let's take a
step back and think
about what unobserved
confounding really is.
So here's a simple
way to think about it.
As we showed earlier,
imagine two columns,
untreated patients on the
left and treated patients
on the right.
For this illustration, let's
focus on the treated side.
Within the treated group, we
can split patients by outcome--
on the left, those with a
good outcome, on the right,
those with a bad outcome.
Now let's zoom in on a single
patient with a bad outcome,
John, and his nearest treated
neighbors with good outcomes--
Mary, Peter, and Tom.
John, Mary, Peter,
and Tom are all
similar in observed
features that
affect this therapy like
AIDS in tumor location,
and they also received
comparable treatment exposure.
However, John had a bad
outcome while his neighbors
had good outcomes.
If according to a
prognostic model
John's predicted baseline risk
looked no worse, perhaps even
better, than his neighbors,
then why did he do worse?
The natural explanation is the
unobserved prognostic burden.
Something not captured in
our recorded covariates
tipped John toward
a bad trajectory.
ROAD3 aims to quantify that
gap through this feature, U,
and then balance it across arms.
Before we compute anything,
here are the assumptions
we'll use for these unobserved
latent factor U. First,
we assume that it increases
a patient's chances
of a bad outcome.
Think of it as unobserved
prognostic burden.
A higher U pushes risk up.
Second, for all patients
with a good outcome,
we set U-I equals 0.
In our example, that means
that the unobserved feature
of Mary, Peter, and Tom is 0.
This doesn't mean
they had no risk.
It means any unobserved
burden did not
tip them into a bad outcome.
Third, for all patients
with a bad outcome,
the unobserved factor U-I leaves
on the interval between 0 and 1
after normalization.
So for John, a--
the unobserved factor U
John will be between 0 and 1
with larger values indicating
more unexplained unobserved
burden consistent with
his adverse trajectory.
Fourth, we assume John,
Mary, Peter, and Tom
have similar treatment effect
since they are neighbors.
Therefore any observed
difference in outcomes
is attributed to only
small dissimilarities
in their observed features or
mainly unobserved factors that
led to different
treatment response.