INSTRUCTOR: We'll now begin
part two of the lecture,
identifying patients who benefit
from treatment using IAI applied
to transformed real-world data.
Let's begin with a
natural question.
Why can't we simply use
the road one framework
that I just presented
to identify patients who
will benefit from treatment?
After all, we
already transformed
the real-world data, corrected
for observed and unobserved
confounding, and even
used interpretable
AI to build actionable
decision rules
and achieve precision medicine.
So what is missing?
The answer lies in understanding
the limitations of the road one
framework, what it can
do, and more importantly,
what it cannot.
Let me explain.
Road one is effective when we
can tune for high sensitivity,
and that makes sense
in two key scenarios.
First, when we can
justify assigning
a large weight because
the treatment benefit
is known to be strong.
This is a classic
landmark RCT scenario
where clear trial data show that
treatment prevents bad outcomes.
Here, road one helps us
safely identify patients
who don't need the treatment
because the treatment works
and missing a true
responder would be costly.
Second, even if the treatments
benefit is modest or uncertain,
we might still
assign a large weight
to preserve high sensitivity,
especially in practice settings
where the treatment
is used by default.
Take, for example,
adjuvant chemotherapy
for colorectal cancer
liver metastasis.
Despite multiple RCTs, the
benefit remains inconclusive.
Yet, many centers routinely
offer it just in case
it helps someone.
So the clinical
goal becomes can we
identify patients who clearly do
not need chemotherapy and spare
them the toxicity of a treatment
they won't benefit from?
In both of these
cases, high sensitivity
helps us focus on
safety by making
sure we don't miss patients
who might actually benefit.
But now, consider a
very different question.
What if our goal is to identify
patients who will actually
benefit from treatment?
Not just those
who might need it,
not just those who are
high risk, but those
who truly improve with therapy.
Think of these patients
with an exon mutation.
They are at high risk, but they
respond poorly to imatinib.
In that case, need and
benefit are not the same.
So here's the problem.
If we blindly tune
for high sensitivity,
we might still assign
treatment to high-risk patients
who don't benefit at all.
That's why the metrics
we used before,
like sensitivity to
tune the weights,
break down when the goal is no
longer to avoid undertreatment,
but to pinpoint who
actually gains from therapy.
In those cases, we need
a different approach.
And that's what we
will explore next.
So how should we
tune the weights
to address unobserved
confounding when our goal is
to identify treatment benefit?
The key idea is
this, use a target
RCT to guide the weight tuning.
By target RCT, I mean
a randomized trial
that was conducted in a cohort
similar to our real-world data
set.
Let's walk through an example.
Suppose we complete step one
of road one in an RWD cohort.
We observe that a five-year
Recurrence-Free Survival,
or RFS, is 39% in
the untreated group
and 40% in the treated group.
That's basically no difference.
But now, we bring in
external knowledge.
In RCT, in a similar population
reports a true treatment effect
corresponding to a
hazard ratio of 0.5.
That's a strong signal.
If we convert that
into five-year RFS
using a Cox proportional
hazards model,
it implies that treated patients
in our RWD should have about 62%
survival at five years.
So what can we do with that?
We can use this RCT
benchmark to guide our model.
We increase the weight
of treated patients
with good outcomes, those who
received treatment ended well,
until our real-world model
starts to recover that 62% are
RFS, matching what the RCT
observed for the treatment
group.
It's a practical way to tune
the model toward the true effect
size.
Sounds simple, right?
But there is a critical caveat.
We have to be sure
the RCT's treatment
effect is transportable
to our real-world cohort.
That is, we can't just
import results from a trial
and expect them to
apply automatically.
To do this validly, we must
ensure that our real-world data
is prognostically similar
to the RCT cohort,
with the exception, of course,
of unobserved confounding, which
the weights are
meant to address.
Let's now revisit
what this methodology
looks like in
practice, specifically,
how chapter 2 of the road
framework builds on chapter 1.
Start on the left
side of the slide.
In road one we performed
prognostic matching
within buckets of baseline risk.
This risk was estimated using
a counterfactual model trained
only on the untreated patients.
Now, in road two, we
take that logic further
and we explicitly emulate the
target RCT in multiple ways.
The additions are
shown in red font
on the right side of the slide.
So what exactly do we add?
Step 1, we apply the eligibility
criteria of the target RCT
to the real-world data.
This ensures we're comparing
similar populations.
Step 2, we still perform
prognostic matching
between treated and
untreated patients,
but now we do two more things.
First, we align the baseline
prognosis of the RWD untreated
and treated groups with that of
the placebo group in the trial.
Why?
Because, in an RCT,
the placebo group
defines the baseline prognosis.
The only difference between
the placebo and treatment arms
is the treatment itself.
So if we want to recover
the treatment effect seen
in the RCT, we need to make
sure the baseline prognosis
of our real-world
patients mirrors that
of the trial placebo group.
Second, we align the
marginal distribution
of important
prognostic variables,
such as KRAS mutational
status or tumor sidedness,
with the trial.
This matters because
baseline prognosis can
be formed in different ways.
A predicted survival
of 50% could
reflect a mix of very
high and very low-risk
patients, or a homogeneous
group all hovering around 50%.
Matching the marginal
covariate distributions,
especially that of
treatment modifiers,
helps us preserve the
structure of the RCT.
By doing both of these,
aligning prognosis
and covariate distributions,
we make an assumption
that this dual alignment also
brings the joint distribution
of prognostic factors in the
RWD close to that in the RCT.
Only after this
careful alignment
do we proceed to step
3, tuning the weights
of treated patients
with good outcomes
to reproduce the treatment
effect observed in the trial.
Let's now take a quick
look under the hood
at the optimization framework
that powers the matching
procedure in road chapter 2.
This expression
may look complex,
but the logic is
straightforward.
The goal is to minimize
the total discrepancy
between our real-world
cohort and the placebo
arm of the target RCT along
several key dimensions.
First, we estimate
baseline prognosis
for each patient using our
counterfactual model which
is trained exclusively on the
untreated real-world group.
We then apply this model
to both treated patients,
denoted i, and untreated
patients, denoted j,
in the real-world data.
Next, we minimize the difference
between the predicted baseline
prognosis for these
two real-world groups
and the actual recurrence risk
observed in the RCT's placebo
arm.
Second, we simultaneously
match on marginal covariate
distributions, ensuring
that prognostic variables
like KRAS status
or tumor location
are represented in the same
proportions in each RWD group
as in the trial population.
Third, we preserve within
bucket prognostic balance,
just as we did in road one.
This ensures a fair comparison
of treated and untreated RWD
patients.
In simple terms, we are solving
a multi-objective matching
problem balancing
baseline prognosis,
covariate distributions,
and internal consistency.
This allows us to build
a real-world cohort that
mirrors the trial population in
both structure and prognosis,
which is the foundation we need
before we tune for treatment
effect.
After completing the two
core transformation steps
we just discussed,
we trained our model
using real-world
data from patients
with colorectal cancer
liver metastasis,
including cohorts from Johns
Hopkins, Cleveland Clinic,
Stanford and other
collaborators.
For external validation,
we used a published
randomized controlled trial,
which appeared in JCO in 2021.
Here is how we
validated the framework.
First, we use our
real-world data
to train optimal
policy trees which
defined subgroups of
patients predicted
to benefit from chemotherapy.
Then we generated
Kaplan-Meier plots
showing actual outcomes within
each of those subgroups.
Next, we reached out to the team
at the National Cancer Center
Hospital in Tokyo, the authors
of the JCO 0603 trial and asked
them to generate the
Kaplan-Meier plots
for our subgroups, but this
time using their RCT data.
This gave us a
unique opportunity
to compare side by side how
the OPT subgroups performed
in real-world versus
trial settings.
We validated our approach
across three levels.
First, direction of benefit.
Did the chemotherapy
subgroup show improvement
in both data sets?
Second level,
statistical significance.
Was the benefit statistically
significant in both data sets?
And the third level,
magnitude of benefit.
Was the improvement in median
recurrence-free survival
similar in both data sets?
If all three
criteria aligned, we
consider the OPT subgroup
successfully validated.
Let's now look at the results
for the first optimal policy
tree.
In the panels on
the upper right,
we grouped together patients
who, according to the first OPT,
should receive
adjuvant chemotherapy.
Panel A shows outcomes in our
real-world emulated cohort,
and panel B shows outcomes
in the RCT cohort.
As you can see, the Kaplan-Meier
curves are visually aligned.
And more importantly, the
benefit from chemotherapy
is statistically significant
in both data sets.
Even more impressive is the
consistency in magnitude.
Median recurrence-free
survival improved from 11
to 33 months in the
real-world cohort,
and from 17 to 41 months
in the RCT cohort.
This is a striking example
of transportability.
A subgroup identified
from real-world data
showed consistent benefit
when applied to an RCT data
set who had no prior access to.
Now look at the lower
right side of the slide.
Here, we grouped patients who
the first OPT predicted would
not benefit from chemotherapy.
Again, panel A is
from our RWD cohort,
and panel B is from the RCT.
As you can see, there is no
clear benefit from chemotherapy
in either cohort.
The curves are
almost overlapping
and the p values
are non-significant.
These results support
two key conclusions.
First, the OPT correctly
identifies treatment responders,
and just as importantly,
it can identify subgroups
with no meaningful
benefit, helping
us avoid unnecessary treatment.
What makes this
especially powerful
is the external validation.
The subgroups were defined
using real-world data performed
similarly in the RCT,
which we had no access to
during development.
Let's now turn to the
second optimal policy tree.
We followed the exact
same validation process.
On the upper right, you
see the Kaplan-Meier plots
for patients who, according
to the second OPT,
were recommended to receive
adjuvant chemotherapy.
Panel A shows the
real-world cohort,
and panel B shows
the RCT cohort.
Once again, the
treatment effect is
visually and statistically
consistent across both data
sets.
The benefit is
statistically significant
and the magnitude of benefit
is nearly identical, 10 versus
32 months in the real-world
cohort and 16 versus 36
months in the RCT cohort.
On the lower right, we focus
on patients who the OPT advised
against chemotherapy.
In both the real-world and RCT
cohorts, there is no benefit.
The Kaplan-Meier
curves are overlapping
and the p values
are not significant.
This reinforces our
earlier findings, first,
that the model
successfully identifies
subgroups who benefit,
and just as importantly,
it identifies subgroups
who don't, helping
us avoid unnecessary treatment.
And again, these
findings were externally
validated in an
independent RCT cohort
that was entirely separate
from model development.
To summarize, in part 2,
we addressed the question,
how can we identify patients
who truly benefit from treatment
using real-world data?
This led to four
key innovations.
First, we introduced a novel
prognostic matching technique
that extracts a cohort
from observational data
and aligns both patient
characteristics and baseline
prognosis with those of the
placebo group in a target RCT.
Second, we developed a
new weight-tuning method
to address unobserved
confounding
by aligning the
post-treatment prognosis
in the real-world
treated group with that
observed in the treated
group of the target RCT.
Third, we demonstrated
the ability
to identify subgroups with
varying levels of treatment
benefit, including those who
receive no benefit at all.
And fourth, we
validated this framework
using a completely
independent RCT data
set, one who had
no prior access to,
ensuring truly unbiased
external validation.
In contrast to part
one of the lecture,
road 2 requires the
existence of a relevant RCT
because you use the trials
results to inform the weights.
So a natural question arises.
Why go through the trouble of
debiasing real-world data if we
already have RCT?
Why not just train
optimal policy trees
directly on the trial data?
At first glance, this might
seem like the simpler path,
but training OPTs on the
biased real-world data
has several key advantages.
First, real world data
is much more abundant.
This abundance allows us to
emulate trials at larger sample
sizes, solving a major issue
in RCTs, low statistical power.
RCTs are often underpowered
because of cost and time
limitations.
This becomes even
more problematic
when doing subgroup
analysis, like we
do with OPTs, which
carve the data set
into smaller and
smaller groups, further
reducing power and precision.
Second, RWD can
include variables
that original RCTs
don't capture.
For example, genomics
and other omics data
are increasingly
available in RWD,
but are often missing
from older trials.
This data can be
biologically meaningful
and add a richer layer
of interpretation.
Importantly, because omics
reflect intrinsic biology,
their distributions are
more likely to be consistent
across data sets, making
them reliable inputs
when aligning RWD to an RCT.
Third, this approach
enables broader access
and faster analysis.
Most RCT data sets
are proprietary,
held by academic groups or
sponsors, but with debiased RWD,
multiple teams can work on a
common emulated trial data set.
This democratizes
precision medicine research
and accelerates discovery.