INSTRUCTOR: To conclude,
let's summarize
what we have covered today.
In part one, we
introduced a new framework
to identify patients who
do not need treatment
using interpretable AI applied
to transformed real-world data.
This helped us
reduce overtreatment
in settings where treatment
efficacy is already
well established.
In part two, we went further.
We introduced a framework
to identify patients
who truly benefit
from treatment, even
when unobserved
confounding is present.
This was achieved by
integrating real-world data
with external RCT
benchmarks and applying
interpretable AI to safely
extrapolate subgroup effects.
In part three, we turned to
RCT data directly and asked,
can interpretable AI outperform
conventional subgroup analysis?
We showed that it
can by identifying
more accurate, data-driven, and
clinically meaningful subgroups.
But something is still missing.
The framework we introduced
in part two, or row two,
does not apply in all cases.
It depends on having a relevant
RCT to guide weight tuning.
So what happens when
there is no such RCT,
or when the RCT exists, but
the trial population is too
different to be informative?
That's where row three comes in.
In the next lecture,
we will show you
how to identify
treatment benefit using
real-world data alone, even
when no randomized trial exists.
Thank you.
And I look forward to continuing
this journey with you.