INSTRUCTOR: So let's begin with
the first part of the lecture.
To illustrate the methodology,
we will use a clinical example.
The efficacy of
adjuvant imatinib
for patients with localized
GIST was established
in the first imatinib
versus placebo trial, which
used broad inclusion criteria.
That means the trial
included patients
with even relatively
low risk of recurrence,
the outcome imatinib
was designed to prevent.
The trial showed a clear benefit
of treating resected GIST
patients with imatinib.
As a result, current selection
guidelines are liberal.
Many patients, including
those with intermediate risk,
receive treatment.
This likely leads
to overtreatment.
However, conducting a new
placebo-controlled RCT
in lower-risk patients
is no longer ethical,
as that would mean
withholding an established,
effective treatment from
half of the participants.
If we are wrong and imatinib is
still needed for some of them,
we could be exposing
those patients
to avoidable recurrence.
This kind of experiment
would be unethical.
And, indeed, 25 years after
the original imatinib trial,
no second placebo arm
study has been done.
So the question
remains, How can we
identify patients who do
not need adjuvant imatinib?
What we will discuss here is
how to transform real-world data
to make it suitable for
identifying patients who do not
need adjuvant imatinib.
Let's start with the top
left Kaplan-Meier plot,
which you have already seen.
It shows the
recurrence-free survival
of patients with
resected GIST based
on whether they
received imatinib.
Counterintuitively, patients
who received imatinib
appear to do worse.
That's a classic example of
confounding by indication.
Those patients were more likely
to be treated because they had
worse prognosis to begin with.
To the right of this plot, I've
included the Kaplan-Meier curve
from the original RCT comparing
imatinib versus placebo.
As you can see, imatinib,
the curve with a solid line,
was highly effective.
It cut the recurrence
risk dramatically,
at least for the
first three years.
This is what the real-world
Kaplan-Meier curve
should look like if
confounding were removed.
Now look at the
bottom left panel.
Here, we show the distribution
of baseline recurrence
risk across our original
real-world cohort.
Baseline risk refers to
the risk of recurrence
if no treatment is given.
To estimate this, we trained
the prognostic model only
on untreated patients and then
applied it to both groups,
including patients
treated with imatinib,
to estimate their
counterfactual baseline risk.
This is a classic
counterfactual approach.
We ask, What would have happened
if this treated patient had not
been treated?
Focus on the bar heights.
You will see that patients
who received imatinib
tend to fall into
higher-risk categories,
while those who didn't fall
into lower-risk categories.
This makes sense.
Clinicians base their treatment
decisions on baseline risk.
We still have many
high-risk patients
who didn't receive imatinib.
This may be from the
preimatinib era or patients
who declined treatment.
This is an example of
observed confounding,
as we were able to
measure it by training
the counterfactual
baseline risk model using
known prognostic variables.
To address this
observed confounding,
we apply prognostic matching.
This isn't ordinary matching
on single variables.
Instead, we match patients
within groups that share
a similar baseline
prognosis estimated
from the counterfactual model.
This safeguard ensures we
are matching only patients
with similar expected outcomes
had they not been treated.
The matching
optimization algorithm
is shown below the
RCT Kaplan-Meier plot.
Now look at the
bottom right panel.
After matching, the treated
and untreated patients
are well balanced across
all baseline risk buckets.
This is a visual check
that our matching worked.
At the top right, you see
the new Kaplan-Meier plot
using only the matched cohort.
Compare it to the original.
The curves are now
nearly overlapping.
There is no longer a large
difference in outcomes.
This is very different from
what we saw before matching.
But also, notice this still
doesn't look like the RCT result
in the center of the figure.
Imatinib showed a clear
benefit in the trial,
and we still don't
see that here.
So while we have addressed
observed confounding,
this shows that unobserved
confounding likely remains.
And that brings us to step
2, which we will cover next.
In step 2, we aim
to do something
that, to our
knowledge, has not been
done before in this setting.
We aim to address unobserved
confounding, which,
by definition, cannot be
corrected directly through
matching or regression, since
you cannot adjust for something
you cannot observe.
Instead, we focus on correcting
the effect of unobserved
confounders, which,
as we saw in step 1,
is that, even after
prognostic matching,
the Kaplan-Meier curve still
suggests no apparent benefit
from imatinib.
That's not because
the drug doesn't work.
It's because unobserved
confounding continues
to distort the signal.
To overcome this,
we use a novel idea.
We artificially amplify the
observed effect of imatinib
to counteract the
downward bias caused
by unobserved confounding.
How do we do that?
We increase the influence
of treated patients
with good outcomes, those who
received imatinib and did not
recur, by assigning them greater
weights during model training.
The model will then try
to make better predictions
for the patients
with a larger weight
since this yields a greater
improvement in the loss
function.
In turn, this will
improve predictions
in a way that pulls the
treatment effect closer
to what we expect from the RCT.
This approach is called
cost-sensitive learning
and is widely used in
machine learning when
working with imbalanced data.
But here, we repurpose it to
correct for confounding bias.
To the best of our
knowledge, this
is the first time
cost-sensitive learning has
been applied in this context.
It's important to emphasize
how we choose the right weight.
We gradually increased
weight until the sensitivity
of the decision tree, tested
on an external data set
from another
institution, reached 90%.
What does this mean?
It means that the tree
now assigns treatment
to at least 90% of patients
who experienced a recurrence.
Why is this important?
Because it ensures
that our model captures
all high-risk patients, even
those whose recurrence might not
have been preventable
by treatment.
This high-sensitivity target
broadens the treatment
assignment, minimizing the
risk of undertreating someone
who truly needs imatinib.
Now that we have completed
the two deconfounding steps,
we are ready to move from
prediction to decision.
We can now estimate the optimal
treatment for a given patient
by comparing their
predicted prognosis
with and without imatinib.
Naturally, we would
choose whichever option
maximizes survival probability.
But there's a problem.
These predictions
are often generated
using black box models,
such as random forests,
and that creates
a major barrier.
Clinicians will not trust
predictions they cannot
understand, so we need a way to
open the black box to understand
what is driving the
model's predictions.
Specifically, we
want to identify
which patient- or tumor-related
characteristics explain
why the model prefers one
treatment over another.
This brings us to Optimal Policy
Trees, or OPTs, such as the one
displayed on this slide.
To assess how well this
decision tree performs,
we tested it in an
independent external cohort.
In the test cohort from Poland,
which included 557 patients,
the decision tree achieved
a sensitivity of 89%
and a specificity of 70%.
In the validation cohort from
Spain, including 411 patients,
the sensitivity was 85%,
and specificity was 57%.
Let's take a moment to
interpret these numbers.
Sensitivity is our safety net.
It reflects the
proportion of patients
who recur and are correctly
assigned to treatment.
So a sensitivity of 89%
means we are catching
almost all high-risk patients.
We are not missing
people who need the drug.
But what is more
exciting is specificity.
This is where the gain happens.
A specificity of 70% means that
we correctly spare treatment
in 70% of patients who would
have received it unnecessarily.
So while sensitivity
keeps us safe,
specificity gives us impact
by reducing overtreatment.
This slide concludes part 1 of
the lecture, where our goal was
to identify patients who
do not need treatment,
those with a good prognosis who
do well even without therapy.
To do that responsibly
using real-world data,
we had to solve two
core challenges--
first, correct for
observed confounding,
and, second, address
unobserved confounding,
which is even harder.
This is where road 1 introduces
three key innovations.
First, it applies a novel
prognostic matching technique
that mimics an
RCT-like population.
We select a subset of
the real-world data
in which treated and
untreated patients have
aligned baseline
prognosis, estimated
using a counterfactual model.
This lets us emulate the
structure of a trial and address
observed confounding.
Second, we go a step further
and address unobserved
confounding through
cost-sensitive learning,
increasing the weight of treated
patients with good outcomes.
We repurpose sensitivity
and specificity
as tuning targets so that
the model emphasizes safety,
by not missing high-risk
patients, and utility,
by minimizing
unnecessary treatment.
Finally, to make
this actionable,
we use optimal policy trees.
These trees produce clinically
interpretable rules,
not black box
predictions, allowing
us to understand and trust how
treatment recommendations are
made.