INSTRUCTOR: Good morning.
I'm Dr. Georgios Antonios
Margonis, and in this lecture,
I'll explain how
artificial intelligence--
specifically
Interpretable AI, or IAI--
can help us achieve
precision medicine.
Let's begin with the overview
figure on this slide.
It summarizes the key concepts
and steps we will cover today,
and it introduces
the terms I will
be using throughout the talk.
We begin with the
two main sources
of medical data, Randomized
Controlled Trials, or RCTs,
and Real-World Data or RWD.
RCT data come from
prospective studies
designed to compare treatments.
These studies are rigorous and
provide high-quality evidence,
but they are also
expensive, time-consuming,
and often limited by
ethical considerations.
As a result, RCT data
are relatively scarce.
In contrast, real-world
data, the byproducts
of routine clinical care,
are abundant and inexpensive.
But that abundance
comes with a price--
bias.
RWD are often affected by
various forms of bias that can
distort treatment comparisons.
So what are these biases?
There are several-- immortal
time bias, selection bias,
and, most problematic,
confounding by indication.
Immortal time bias
and selection bias
can typically be addressed
with appropriate study
design and analytic methods.
However, confounding, especially
unobserved confounding,
is much harder to control
for and often cannot be fully
addressed with current methods.
To illustrate confounding,
look at the Kaplan-Meier plot
on the slide.
It shows patients with resected
GIST, a gastrointestinal tumor.
The blue curve
represents those who
received adjuvant imatinib, the
red curve those who did not.
Paradoxically, the
group receiving imatinib
appears to do worse.
But we know from RCTs that
imatinib is effective.
This is confounding at work.
Patients who received
imatinib likely
had more aggressive disease--
for example, high
mitotic counts.
This made clinicians
prescribe treatment,
but it also independently
predicted poor outcomes.
And this is the essence of a
confounder, a variable that
influences both treatment
assignment and patient outcome.
When the confounder is
recorded, such as mitotic count,
you can adjust for it with
matching or regression.
But when confounders are
unmeasured, or even unknown,
the analysis becomes risky.
RCTs solve this problem.
Randomization balances both
known and unknown confounders
across treatment arms.
That means any
differences in outcomes
can be attributed
directly to the treatment.
In this lecture, I will
walk you through how
we can use AI and optimization
methods to address
both observed and unobserved
confounding in RWD, making
it possible to generate
causal treatment insights even
outside of trials.
Once bias is accounted for--
or absent, in the case of RCTs--
we can turn to our goal,
precision medicine.
According to the National
Cancer Institute,
oncologic precision
medicine is the use
of specific information
about a person's tumor
to help plan treatment.
Put simply, we want to move
from what works best on average
to what works best for
this individual patient.
But even when we have data
from RCTs, or the biased RWD,
we don't always achieve
precision medicine.
RCTs tell us what
works on average,
but the average effect can
hide important variation.
To move toward
patient-specific treatment,
we need to uncover subgroups--
patients who benefit, patients
who don't, and patients who
may not need treatment at all.
That's where
interpretable AI comes in.
Using methods like
optimal policy trees,
we can define
treatment-relevant subgroups
in both RCT and RWD settings.
These trees do not
output probabilities.
They output clear,
rule-based groupings
based on clinical features.
This makes the results
interpretable, inspectable,
and testable, allowing us to
assess whether the identified
subgroups are
clinically meaningful.
This brings us to
the final goal,
illustrated in the pie chart.
We aim to first
identify patients
who do not need treatment,
those with good prognoses
who do well regardless.
Then, among those who
do need treatment,
we distinguish between those
who will actually benefit
and those who will not because
not all high-risk patients
respond.
Now let's look at how this
lecture is structured.
It will be divided
into three parts.
First, I will discuss how to
use real-world data to identify
patients who do not
need treatment--
those with good prognoses
who do well regardless.
Second, I will describe how to
use real-world data to identify,
among those who do need
treatment, who will actually
benefit and who will not because
not all high-risk patients
respond.
And, finally, in part
3, I will explain
how to use IAI on
randomized trial data
to identify patients
who actually
benefit from a treatment.
So let's begin with the
first part of the lecture.
We will explore how to transform
real-world data to identify
patients who do not
need treatment--
those with good prognoses
who do well regardless.