INSTRUCTOR: Now,
let's look at what
happens on observational
cohorts when
we try to recover
the treatment effect.
We attempt to recover
the hazard ratio
as reported in prior
clinical trials
of the respective therapies.
The dashed red
line in each figure
is the trial benchmark
for that setting.
The bars show four estimators
on the same real-world data--
the original naive estimate, a
multivariable Cox adjustment,
prognostic matching, the
first step only of road one,
and the full road
three pipeline.
On the left, we can
see the GIST data
set, which contains patient.
And for these patients,
we need to decide
whether we are going to
prescribe imatinib or just
observation.
In GIST, the RCT, the randomized
clinical trial benchmark,
is around a hazard
ratio of 0.46.
Starting from the raw
cohort, the original estimate
is badly distorted.
It is well above 2, which is
definitely the wrong direction.
Simply adding covariates
in multivariable analysis
pulls the estimate down,
and prognostic matching
helps a bit more.
But neither reaches
the trial target.
After we add road three's
latent burden balancing
on top of the prognostic
match, the hazard ratio
aligns with the trial right
around the dashed line.
In GIST, key prognostic features
like size, mitotic count,
and tumor site carry
a lot of signal.
So once we control observed
prognoses and balance
the residual latent burden, the
cohort behaves as if randomized,
and we recover the
trial-like effect.
In the right figure, you can
see results on the RPS cohort.
The RPS cohort contains patients
with retroperitoneal sarcoma.
And we want to either prescribe
preoperative radiotherapy
or not.
For this cohort, the dashed
line, the ground truth,
is around 0.75.
The original observational
estimate is far from that,
and multivariable
analysis doesn't fix it.
They both remain too
optimistic about the effect
of radiotherapy.
Prognostic matching
improves the estimate.
We move towards the dashed line.
But there is still a gap.
With road three, once we balance
the latent unobserved factor
across arms, the estimate
lands near the benchmark,
and the error bars tighten.
An interesting observation
is that our method
correct the treatment
effect estimation
in both and over and
underestimation scenario,
left and right.
Now, in the next set
of results we have,
we start from RCTs, where we
know the true hazard ratio.
These cohorts are balanced.
So in order to make them more
observation-like cohorts,
we intentionally inject bias
to mimic the real world.
We do this by
randomly resampling
patients with bad outcomes and
adding them back in the cohort.
That basically inflates
poor outcomes in a way
that correlates with
treatment assignment,
creating selection bias, like in
observational real-life cohorts.
The dashed red line marks
the true trial hazard ratio
before we inject bias, and
this is the hazard ratio
we want to recover
after the road three
pipeline is implemented.
So focusing on the
left, we have STRASS.
STRASS is a randomized
clinical trial
that was conducted on
patients with, again,
primary retroperitoneal
sarcomas, again, regarding
preoperative radiotherapy.
After injecting confounding, the
original estimate jumps above 1.
Multivariable adjustment
helps but still overshoots.
Prognostic matching gets
closer but not on target.
With road three, after balancing
the latent unobserved burden,
the estimate returns
to approximately 1,
and the error bars
tighten again.
Now, on the right, we
have the BRT cohort.
This data set contains patients
with extremity sarcomas.
The question here is also should
they get radiotherapy or not.
The injected bias pushes
original and multivariable
analysis toward 1, toward
basically no effect.
Prognostic matching partially
correct the treatment effect.
However, it is road three that
actually pulls the estimate down
to approximately 0.5,
recovering the protective signal
of the therapy.
A small gap remains because
for this specific data set,
we have a smaller
effective sample.
But our result is much closer
to truth than the alternatives.
To summarize, road three
builds on road one's
prognostic matching by
adding a principled way
to quantify and balance
unobserved prognostic factors
in observational survival data
without requiring a target
randomized clinical trial.
After balancing
this latent factor
and refitting a
multivariable Cox model,
we obtain hazard
ratio estimates that
are trial-like on
real-world cohorts
and stable under
strong stress tests,
as we did with randomized
clinical trial cohorts, where,
as we said, we injected
artificial confounding.
This is a practical path to
credible effect estimation
and actionable precision
medicine in settings where
trials are absent or
incomplete, since one can now
use the RCT-like cohort created
through the road three pipeline
train, for example,
optimal policy trees
to get specific policies or
treatment recommendations
for each cohort subset.
Thank you for
listening, and good luck
with the rest of the modules.