INSTRUCTOR: Now let's
focus on the intuition
behind constructing U. We wanted
to cover two distinct scenarios.
In the first scenario,
John has a worse prognosis
than his neighbors,
Mary, Peter, and Tom.
John's bad outcome is mostly
explained by observed features.
The model already
expected him to be
in higher risk than similarly
treated patients who did well.
In other words, there is little
residual unobserved burden
to explain.
In this case, we want his
unobserved factor, U John,
to be low.
In the second scenario,
John has better prognosis
than his neighbors.
John did worse than expected
given his observed prognosis,
so his bad outcome is not
explained by observed features.
That gap is precisely what
we call unobserved prognostic
burden, so we want his
unobserved factor, U John,
to be high.
Now which formula can capture
these scenarios successfully?
We score everyone with a
prognostic model trained
on the untreated cohort.
So the scores reflect
baseline disease scores.
And we find John's K nearest
treated neighbors who
had good outcomes, in this
case as we said Mary, Peter,
and Tom, so K equals 3.
We compare John's predicted
risk, P John, to the average
predicted risk of his neighbors.
The raw quantity
that gives U John
is the difference between P
John and the average baseline
prognosis of his neighbors,
which we later normalize
into 0, 1 to get U tilde John.
Now how does this quantity
satisfy our two scenarios?
In the first scenario,
John has worse prognosis
than his neighbors.
If P John is lower than
his neighbor's average,
then after normalization,
U tilde John lands near 0.
In the second scenario,
John has better prognosis
than his neighbors.
If P John is higher, meaning
he looked healthier on observed
covariates, then U--
U tilde John increases
and moves toward 1.
We perform the
exact same approach
for all the untreated patients
with bad outcomes, too,
and we again normalize
their unobserved quantity.
There are a few design
choices we need to make.
First are the prognostic model.
Linear Cox models trained
on untreated patients
work well and avoid overfitting.
Second, the number of neighbors.
We avoid choosing a very small
number of neighbors like 1
due to instability.
Values like 3 to 5
are typically robust.
Empirically, road three is
robust across reasonable choices
of prognostic model,
number of neighbors,
and neighborhood density.
Once we have our
utility quantity,
we do not insert it
into the matching step.
It is strongly correlated
with the outcome
and would distort distances.
Instead following the frequency
weighting approach or row
weighting approach
from road one,
we compute a single
scalar weight
for the treated group
with good outcomes
so that the weighted
mean of U tilde
becomes matched between
treated and untreated arms.
This is the minimal control
that balances the latent factors
distribution between
the two treatment arms
without overfitting
small cohorts.
After waiting, we fit a
multivariable Cox model
on the transformed cohort
including treatment and baseline
covariates to estimate
the final hazard ratio.
So to summarize, the
three steps are we first
perform road one
prognostic matching
to fix observed confounding.
Second, we compute U
tilde and balance it
across treatment arms
via scalar weight.
And, three, we run a Cox
model on the balanced cohort
to obtain the hazard ratio.
That's road three end to end.